Register of the Dachau (Germany: Concentration Camp) Miscellaneous Records
Hoover Institution Archives
Dachau (Germany: Concentration Camp) miscellaneous records,
1943-1945
52010
Dachau (Concentration camp)
1 manuscript box, 1 oversize box (0.8 linear feet)
Hoover Institution on War, Revolution, and Peace Stanford, California 94305-6010
Prisoner lists, supply lists, and miscellany, relating to operations of the camp during World War II. Also available on microfilm (1 reel).
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for research.
Acquisition Information
Acquired.
Accruals
Increments may have been received since this finding aid was prepared. Please check Stanford University's online catalog Socrates at http://library.stanford.edu/webcat to find the full extent of the collection.
Alternative Forms of Material Available
Also available on microfilm (1 reel).
Historical Note
German concentration camp.
Scope and Content Note
The Dachau Concentration Camp miscellaneous records consist of material donated by Willem Houwink, a prisoner at the camp who was able to take scattered documents at the time of the camp's liberation on April 29, 1945.
Most of the material relates to records of the clothing supply department of the camp, including inventories and individual requests for shoes and clothing. Of special interest are lists of prisoners indicating their name, time of arrival, and date of death or escape.
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the repository's online public access catalog.
Subjects
Germany.; World War, 1939-1945.; Concentration camps--Germany.; World War, 1939-1945--Concentration camps.
Container List
- Building Plan, 1943. (Box 1)
  Pen and ink building plan of Dachau Concentration Camp. Includes list of buildings and their designated use
  - Plan of Dachau with structures identified by number ("Gebäude-Ubersichts-Plan"), 1943. (Folder 1: 1-2)
    Pen and ink drawing. Includes a typewritten list of camp buildings and their designated use ("Gebäude-Ubersicht vom SS-Lager Dachau")
- Prisoners File, 1945. (Box 1)
  Lists of prisoners indicating arrivals, deaths, transfers, releases, and escapes. Lists include name, camp identification number, and category of each prisoner. Arranged chronologically
  Lists of prisoners indicating arrivals, deaths, transfers, releases, and escapes, 1945. Lists include name, camp identification number, and category of each prisoner. Typescript
  - January
    - 17-18 (Folder 1: 3)
    - 19-21 (Folder 1: 4)
    - 23-26 (Folder 1: 5)
    - 27-30 (Folder 1: 6)
  - February, 1-2 (Folder 1: 7)
  - March
    - 1-5 (Folder 1: 8)
    - 6-10 (Folder 1: 9)
    - 11-15 (Folder 1: 10)
    - 16-20 (Folder 1: 11)
    - 21-25 (Folder 1: 12)
    - 26-31 (Folder 1: 13)
  - April
    - 1-10. (Folder 1: 14)
      List for April 4 includes names of Danes and Norwegians released to the Swedish Red Cross
    - 11-17 (Folder 1: 15)
    - 18-21 (Folder 1: 16)
    - 22-26 (Folder 1: 17)
- Supply File, 1943-1945. (Box 1)
  Inventories, lists, and requests for clothing and shoes. Arranged alphabetically by camp subdivision
  - General
    - Prescriptions from medical department and requests for leather shoes for individual prisoners ("Arztlische Bescheinigungen Lederschuhe"), 1943-1945 (Folder 1: 18)
    - Monthly inventories of prisoners' clothing, 1944 November - 1945 March. (Folder 1: 19)
      Handwritten
  - Arbeitslager Allach. Clothing department. Inventories of clothing, requests for clothing supplies, and lists of clothing and shoes of prisoners transferred to other camps, 1943 June - 1944 November. (Folder 1: 20)
    Handwritten and typescript
  - Arbeitslager Blaichach and Kommando Bad Tolz
    - Inventories of clothing and orders for clothing supplies. (Folder 1: 21)
    - Receipt from Bayerische Motorenwerke AG., 1944 August 26 (Folder 1: 22)
- Oversize File, n.d. (Box 2)
  Cardboard wall plaques listing inventories of clothing and shoes
  - Cardboard wall plaques listing inventories of clothing and shoes, n.d. (Box 2)